Farhana Shahid

Research Interests

My research interests encompass the diverse spectra of Human-Computer Interaction, Social Computing, and Ubiquitous Computing. I have broad interest in the design, use, and social impact of technologies that create sustainable outcomes for traditionally underserved and low-resource communities.

Education ____

Ph.D. in Information Science 2021 - Present

CORNELL UNIVERSITY GPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Advisor: Aditya Vashistha

M.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering 2017 – 2019

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology GPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Advisor: A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering 2013 – 2017

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology GPA: 3.74 out of 4.00

Advisor: A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

Appointments _____

Cornell University Ithaca, New York

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT Summer 2021 – Summer 2022

Graduate Teaching Assistant Fall 2021, Fall 2022

Brac University Dhaka, Bangladesh

LECTURER May 2018 – May 2021

Eastern University

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Sep 2017 - Apr 2018

Academic Awards and Honors

- 2022 **Finalist: HCI Social Media, People, and Society**, Meta PhD Research Fellowship
- 2020 **Distinguished Paper Award (Top 3%), IMWUT Volume 3**
- 2020 Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%), CSCW2020
- 2016 University Merit Scholarship, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology
- 2015 **Dean's List Award**, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology
- 2015 First runner up: Poster Presentation Session, Esonance, Islamic University of Technology
- 2012 Champion: Science Olympiad, Inter College Science Festival, Holy Cross College
- 2011 First runner up, 4th Bangladesh Chemistry Olympiad
- 2011 Secondary School Merit Scholarship, Education Board of Dhaka

Publications

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

1. **Farhana Shahid**, Srujana Kamath, Annie Sidotam, Vivian Jiang, Alexa Batino, and Aditya Vashistha. 2022. "It Matches My Worldview": Examining Perceptions and Attitudes Around Fake Videos. In *CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2022)*.

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Farhana Shahid**, Shrirang Mare, and Aditya Vashistha. 2022. Examining Source Effects on Perceptions of Fake News in Rural India. 2022. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*. Vol. 6, No. CSCW1, Article 89 (April 2022).
- 2. **Farhana Shahid**, Wasifur Rahman, Mohammad Saifur Rahman, Sharmin Akther Purabi, Ayesha Seddiqa, Moin Mostakim, Farhan Feroz, Tanjir Rashid Soron, Fahmida Hossain, Nabila Khan, Anika Binte Islam, Nipi Paul, Ehsan Hoque, and A. B. M. Alim Al Islam.

- 2020. Leveraging Free-Hand Sketches for Potential Screening of PTSD. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies*. Vol. 4, No. 3, Article 94 (September 2020).
- 3. **Farhana Shahid**, Shahinul Hoque Ony, Takrim Rahman Albi, Sriram Chellappan, Aditya Vashistha, and A. B. M. Alim Al Islam. 2020. Learning from Tweets: Opportunities and Challenges to Inform Policy Making During Dengue Epidemic. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*. Vol. 4, No. CSCW1, Article 65 (May 2020). **CSCW Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%)**
- 4. **Farhana Shahid**, Wasifur Rahman, Anika Binte Islam, Nipi Paul, Nabila Khan, Mohammad Saifur Rahman, Md Munirul Haque, and A. B. M. Alim Al Islam. 2019. Two Tell-tale Perspectives of PTSD: Neurobiological Abnormalities and Bayesian Regulatory Network of the Underlying Disorder in a Refugee Context. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies*. Vol. 3, No. 3, Article 101 (September 2019). **▼ IMWUT Distinguished Paper Award (Top 3%)**

THESIS

- 1. Leveraging Features from EEG and Free-Hand Sketches for Effective Diagnosis of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder, M.Sc. Engg. Thesis, In Department of Computer Science and Engineering, BUET, 2021.
- 2. Blending Statistical Measures with Artificial Intelligence for Predicting Inter Species Gene Expressions, B.Sc. Engg. Thesis, In *Department of Computer Science and Engineering, BUET*, 2017.

MAGAZINE PUBLICATIONS

1. Rahul Majethia, Shreya Ghosh, Hannah R. Nolasco, **Farhana Shahid**, Varun Viswanath, Ibrahim Shehi Shehu, and Yiran Zhao. 2022. Stepping Into the Next Decade of Ubiquitous and Pervasive Computing: UbiComp and ISWC 2021. In *IEEE Pervasive Computing*. Vol. 21, No. 2, (June 2022).

Teaching Experience _____

TEACHING ASSISTANT

• Computing and Global Development (Fall 2022, Fall 2021)

COURSE INSTRUCTOR

- Computer Graphics (Spring 2021, Fall 2020, Summer 2020, Spring 2020, Fall 2019, Summer 2019, Spring 2019, Spring 2018)
- Pattern Recognition (Fall 2020, Summer 2020)
- Artificial Intelligence (Spring 2020, Fall 2019)
- Object Oriented Programming (Fall 2019, Summer 2019, Spring 2019, Fall 2018, Summer 2018)
- Digital Logic Design (Spring 2020, Summer 2018)
- Algorithms (Summer 2019, Fall 2019, Summer 2018)
- Data Structures (Summer 2019, Summer 2018)
- Operating Systems (Spring 2018, Fall 2017)
- Mathematical Analysis for Computer Science (Fall 2017)

COURSE COORDINATOR

- Computer Graphics (Spring 2021, Fall 2020, Spring 2020, Fall 2019)
- Pattern Recognition (Fall 2020, Summer 2020)
- Artificial Intelligence (Summer 2020, Spring 2020, Fall 2019)
- Object Oriented Programming (Fall 2020, Fall 2019)

MENTORING

UNDERGRADUATE STUDENTS

- Takrim Rahman Albi
- · Shahinul Hoque Ony

Services_____

REVIEWER

| 2020-22 | ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) |
|---------|---|
| 2021–22 | ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW) |
| 2022 | ACM SIGCAS Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS) |
| 2020 | ACM Transactions on Computing for Healthcare |

ORGANIZING COMMITTEE

| 2022 | Publicity Co-chair, ACM COMPASS |
|------|--|
| 2018 | 5 th Eastern University Math Olympiad, Eastern University |

UNIVERSITY SERVICE

2022–Present IS Seminar Co-coordinator, Information Science Graduate Student Association, Cornell University

2021–22 Vice President, Information Science Graduate Student Association, Cornell University

2019–20 AI, ML, and NLP thesis panel, Brac University
 2019 Course curriculum update, Brac University
 2018 Semester planning, Brac University

VOLUNTEER

2022 CHI 2022, CSCW 2022

2021 CHI 2021, UbiComp 2021, CSCW 2021, Asia-Ocenia Accessibility Workshop

2015 National High School Programming Contest, BUET

Selected Talks_

CONFERENCE TALKS

May 2022 "It Matches My Worldview": Examining Perceptions and Attitudes Around Fake Videos, CHI 2022
Learning from Tweets: Opportunities and Challenges to Inform Policy Making During Dengue

Oct 2020 Epidemic, CSCW 2020

Sep 2020 Leveraging Free-Hand Sketches for Potential Screening of PTSD, UbiComp 2020

3